Woodbury Lowery Collection Relating to Spanish Settlements in the United States
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Woodbury Lowery Collection Relating to Spanish Settlements in the United States 1517-1803
MSS30676
Lowery, Woodbury, 1853-1906
2,000 items
18 containers
2.4 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer, editor and historian. Chiefly handwritten transcripts of documents compiled by Lowery relating to Spanish settlements in California, Florida, Louisiana, New Mexico, and Texas.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Lowery, Woodbury, 1853-1906.
Subjects
Frontier and pioneer life--California.; Frontier and pioneer life--Florida.; Frontier and pioneer life--Louisiana.; Frontier and pioneer life--New Mexico.; Frontier and pioneer life--Texas.; Spaniards--California.; Spaniards--Florida.; Spaniards--Louisiana.; Spaniards--New Mexico.; Spaniards--Texas.
Places
California--History--To 1846.; Florida--History--To 1821.; Louisiana--History--To 1803.; New Mexico--History--To 1848.; Spain--Colonies--America.; Texas--History--To 1846.
Occupations
Editors.; Historians.; Lawyers.
Provenance
The Woodbury Lowery Collection Relating to Spanish Settlements in the United States was a gift of the Lowery estate in 1907.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Maps and a card catalog describing them have been transferred to the Geography and Map Division. A publication by Fr. Juan Bernejo, Exposicion de puntas pertenecientes a la Provincia de Santa Elena de la Florida (Seville, 1739), has been transferred to the Rare Book and Special Collections Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the Woodbury Lowery Collection Relating to Spanish Settlements in the United States.
Access and Restrictions
The Woodbury Lowery Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of Woodbury Lowery (1853-1906) relating to Spanish settlements in the United States spans the years 1517-1803 and consists of bound volumes of material gathered and organized by Woodbury for the preparation of his unfinished history of “Spanish Settlements within the Present Limits of the United States,” containing catalog records and handwritten transcripts of documents concerning California, Florida, Louisiana, New Mexico, and Texas.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Container List
- Florida (Box 1)
  - Catalog, 1517-1800 (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts (Box 2)
    - 1551-1565 (Box 2)
    - 1566-1579 (Box 3)
    - 1580-1597 (Box 4)
    - 1598-1602 (Box 5)
    - 1603-1607 (Box 6)
    - 1608-1620 (Box 7)
    - 1621-1657 (Box 8)
    - 1658-1676 (Box 9)
    - 1677-1800 (Box 10)
- New Mexico, California, Texas, and Louisiana: catalog (Box 11)
- New Mexico (Box 12)
  - 1538-1626 (Box 12)
  - 1555-1583 (Box 13)
  - 1584-1600 (Box 14)
  - 1601-1680 (Box 15)
  - 1681-1800 (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous records, 1522-17th century (Box 17)
- California, 1588-1800 (Box 18)
- Texas, 1673-1803 (Box 18)
- Louisiana, 1766-1803 (Box 18)